<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Configuring Maven</title>
    <author email="brett@apache.org">Brett Porter</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Configuring Maven">
      <p>
        Maven configuration occurs at 3 levels:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <i>Project</i> - most static configuration occurs in
          <code>pom.xml</code>
        </li>
        <li>
          <i>Installation</i> - this is configuration added once for a Maven installation (not supported in the initial Technology Preview)
        </li>
        <li>
          <i>User</i> - this is configuration specific to a particular user
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        The separation is quite clear - the project defines information that applies to the project, no matter who is
        building it, while the others both define settings for the current environment.
      </p>
      <p>
        <b>Note: </b> the installation and user configuration can not be used to add shared project information -
        for example setting
        <code>&lt;organization&gt;</code> or
        <code>&lt;distributionManagement&gt;</code> company-wide.
        For this, you should have your projects inherit from a company-wide parent
        <code>pom.xml</code>.
        <!-- TODO: versioning doc that discusses this -->
      </p>
      <p>
        You can specify your user configuration in <code>${user.home}/.m2/settings.xml</code>. A
        <a href="settings-descriptor.html">full reference</a> to the
        configuration file is available. This section will show how to make some common configurations.
        Note that the file is not required - defaults will be used if it is not found.
      </p>
      <p style="font-weight: bold; font-size: larger">
        Configuring your Local Repository
      </p>
      <p>
        The local repository is part of a profile in your user configuration. You can have multiple profiles, with one
        set to active so that you can switch environments.
      </p>
      <source><![CDATA[
<settings>
  .
  .
  <profiles>
    <profile>
      <active>true</active>
      <localRepository>/path/to/local/repo</localRepository>
    </profile>
  </profiles>
  .
  .]]></source>
      <p>
        The local repository must be an absolute path.
      </p>
      <p style="font-weight: bold; font-size: larger">
        Configuring a Proxy
      </p>
      <p>
        You can configure a proxy to use for some or all of your HTTP requests in Maven 2.0. The username and
        password are only required if your proxy requires basic authentication (note that later alphas will support
        storing your passwords in a secured keystore - in the mean time, please ensure your <code>settings.xml</code>
        file is secured with permissions appropriate for your operating system).
      </p>
      <p>
        The <code>nonProxyHosts</code> setting accepts wild cards, and each host not to proxy is separated by the
        <code>|</code> character. This matches the
        <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/docs/guide/net/properties.html">JDK configuration</a> equivalent.
      </p>
      <source><![CDATA[
<settings>
  .
  .
  <proxies>
   <proxy>
      <active>true</active>
      <protocol>http</protocol>
      <host>proxy.somewhere.com</host>
      <port>8080</port>
      <username>proxyuser</username>
      <password>somepassword</password>
      <nonProxyHosts>www.google.com|*.somewhere.com</nonProxyHosts>
    </proxy>
  </proxies>
  .
  .]]></source>
      <p style="font-weight: bold; font-size: larger">
        Security and Deployment Settings
      </p>
      <p>
        Repositories to deploy to are defined in a project in the <code>&lt;distributionManagement&gt;</code> section.
        However, you cannot put your username, password, or other security settings in that project. For that reason,
        you should add a server definition to your own settings with an <code>id</code> that matches that of the
        deployment repository in the project.
      </p>
      <p>
        In addition, some repositories may require authorisation to download from, so the corresponding settings can
        be specified in a <code>server</code> element in the same way.
      </p>
      <p>
        Which settings are required will depend on the type of repository you are deploying to. As of the first release,
        only SCP deployments and file deployments are supported by default, so only the following SCP configuration
        is needed:
      </p>
      <source><![CDATA[
<settings>
  .
  .
  <servers>
    <server>
      <id>repo1</id>
      <username>repouser</username>
      <!-- other optional elements:
        <password>my_login_password</password>
        <privateKey>/path/to/identity</privateKey> (default is ~/.ssh/id_dsa)
        <passphrase>my_key_passphrase</passphrase>
      -->
    </server>
  </servers>
  .
  .]]></source>
      <p style="font-weight: bold; font-size: larger">
        Using Mirrors for Repositories
      </p>
      <p>
        Repositories are declared inside a project, which means that if you have your own custom repositories, those
        sharing your project easily get the right settings out of the box. However, you may want to use an alternative
        mirror for a particular repository without changing the project files.
      </p>
      <p>
        Some reasons to use a mirror are:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>There is a synchronized mirror on the internet that is geographically closer and faster</li>
        <li>You want to replace a particular repository with your own internal repository which you have greater
          control over</li>
        <li>You want to run maven-proxy to provide a local cache to a mirror and need to use it's URL instead</li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        To configure a mirror of a given repository, you provide it in your settings file, giving the new repository
        it's own <code>id</code> and <code>url</code>, and specify the <code>mirrorOf</code> setting that is the ID of
        the repository you are using a mirror of. For example, the ID of the main Maven repository included by default is
        <code>central</code>, so to use an Australian mirror, you would configure the following:
      </p>
      <source><![CDATA[
<settings>
  .
  .
  <mirrors>
   <mirror>
      <id>planetmirror</id>
      <name>Australian Mirror of http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/</name>
      <url>http://public.planetmirror.com/maven2/</url>
      <mirrorOf>central</mirrorOf>
    </mirror>
  </mirrors>
  .
  .]]></source>
      <p>
        <i>Please note:</i> this particular is not actually set up for Maven 2 yet, so this should be treated as an
        example only.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

