<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Dependency Mechanism</title>
    <author email="brett@apache.org">Brett Porter</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Dependency Mechanism">
      <p>
        There are many aspects to working with dependencies in Maven. While it is not the sole focus of Maven, it
        does comprise a large and important part of the system.
      </p>
      <p>
        This document is currently in the process of being written, so not all facets are covered.
      </p>
      <subsection name="Transitive Dependencies">
        <p>
          Transitive dependencies are a new feature in Maven 2.0. This allows you to avoid needing to discover and
          specify the libraries that your own dependencies require, and including them automatically.
        </p>
        <p>
          This feature is facilitated by reading the project files of your dependencies from the remote repositories
          specified. In general, all dependencies of those projects are used in your project, as are any that the
          project inherits from its parents, or from its dependencies, and so on.
        </p>
        <p>
          There is no limit to the number of levels that dependencies can be gathered from, and will only cause a problem
          if a cyclic dependency is discovered.
        </p>
        <p>
          With transitive dependencies, the graph of included libraries can quickly grow quite large. For this reason,
          there are some additional features that will limit which dependencies are included:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <i>Dependency mediation</i> - this determines what version of a dependency will be used when multiple
            different ones are encountered. Currently, Maven 2.0 only supports using the "nearest definition" - so
            you can always guarantee a version by declaring it explicitly in the project's POM.
          </li>
          <li>
            <i>Dependency scope</i> - this allows you to only include dependencies appropriate for the current stage
            of the build. This is described in more detail below.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          More features are planned, such as different mediation techniques and conflict management as well as reporting,
          in later alpha versions of Maven 2.0.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Dependency Scope">
        <p>
          Dependency scope is used to limit the transitivity of a depedency, and also to affect the classpath used for
          various build tasks.
        </p>
        <p>
          There are 4 scopes available:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <b>compile</b> - this is the default scope, used if none is specified. Compile dependencies are available
            in all classpaths.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>provided</b> - this is much like compile, but indicates you expect the JDK or a container to provide it.
            It is only available on the compilation classpath, and is not transitive.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>runtime</b> - this scope indicates that the dependency is not required for compilation, but is for execution.
            It is in the runtime and test classpaths, but not the compile classpath.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>test</b> - this scope indicates that the dependency is not required for normal use of the application, and
            is only available for the test compilation and execution phases.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          Each of the scopes affects transitive dependencies in different ways, as is demonstrated in the table below.
          If a dependency is set to the scope in the left column, dependencies with the scope across the top row will
          result in a dependency in the main project with the scope listed at the intersection. If no scope is listed,
          it means the dependency will be omitted.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th></th>
            <th>compile</th>
            <th>provided</th>
            <th>runtime</th>
            <th>test</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>compile</th>
            <td>compile (*)</td>
            <td>-</td>
            <td>runtime</td>
            <td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>provided</th>
            <td>provided</td>
            <td>provided</td>
            <td>provided</td>
            <td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>runtime</th>
            <td>runtime</td>
            <td>-</td>
            <td>runtime</td>
            <td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>test</th>
            <td>test</td>
            <td>-</td>
            <td>test</td>
            <td>-</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          <b>(*) Note: </b> it is intended that this should be runtime instead, so that all compile dependencies must
          be explicitly listed - however, there is the case where the library you depend on extends a class from another
          library, forcing you to have available at compile time. For this reason, compile time dependencies remain
          as compile scope even when they are transitive.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

