<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Road Map</title>
    <author email="brett@apache.org">Brett Porter</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Development Road Map for Maven 2.0">
      <p>
        This document discusses the release plans and current roadmap for Maven 2.0.
      </p>
      <p>
        We are working to a 4-5 week release cycle, meaning that there will be at least one release per month.
      </p>
      <p>
        The first releases such as the technology preview will be designated "alpha" releases, indicating that
        they are not yet feature complete and there are outstanding bugs. Following that, "beta" releases will be
        made available where introduction of new features will be restricted and the focus on improving usability and
        stability. Finally, one or more release candidates will be distributed for testing that are genuinely believed
        to be final, with the expectation that a final release would be available shortly afterwards.
      </p>
      <p>
        We will continue with the successful technique from Maven 1.0 of making plugins available on a separate
        release schedule so that new features can be obtained as they are ready and tested.
      </p>
      <subsection name="Maven 2.0 beta 1">
        <p>
          <i>Expected Release:</i>mid-July 2005
        </p>
        <p>
          <i>Aims and features:</i>This should be feature complete and mostly stable. There are expected to be
          bug fixes and cosmetic changes, but no new major features beyond this release.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Plugins will be nearing their first final releases</li>
          <li>Shared development environment support</li>
          <li>Minor cosmetic features</li>
          <li>Bugfixes</li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Maven 2.0 Final">
        <p>
          <i>Expected Release:</i>early August 2005, following a release candidate
        </p>
        <p>
          <i>Aims and features:</i>Final release, a suitable replacement for Maven 1.1 as the stable release for new
          projects.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Plugin releases</li>
          <li>Bugfixes</li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Maven 2.0.x">
        <p>
          <i>Aims and features:</i>Bugfixes found in the Maven core will be released as interim updates leading up
          to the Maven 2.1 development stream.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Maven 2.1">
        <p>
          <i>Aims and features:</i>Features to be added after the July freeze on Maven 2.0 will be slated for a 2.1
          release later in 2005.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

