<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
/*
 * Copyright 2001-2004 The Apache Software Foundation.
 * 
 * Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 * you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 * You may obtain a copy of the License at
 * 
 *      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 * 
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 */
 -->

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Maven 2.0 - Mojo API Specification</title>
    <author email="jdcasey@apache.org">John Casey</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Introduction">
      <p>Starting with Maven 2.0, plugins can be written in Java or any of a 
        number of scripting languages (currently just marmalade - we are 
        working to implement others). Additionally, Maven tries to stay out of 
        the way of the programmer with its new Mojo API. This opens up the 
        opportunity for many Mojos to be reused outside of Maven, or bridged 
        into Maven from external systems like Ant.</p>
      <p>NOTE: For now, we will limit the discussion to Java-based mojos, since 
        each scripting language will present these same basic requirements with 
        various forms of implementation.</p>
      <p>Although the requirements on Mojos are minimal by design, there are 
        still a very few requirements that Mojo developers must keep in mind. <!-- First, a Mojo must have a method named <code>execute</code> which 
        declares no parameters, and has a void return type. If this method 
        throws an exception, that exception must either be a derivative of 
        <code>java.lang.RuntimeException</code>, or a derivative of 
        <code>org.apache.maven.plugin.MojoExecutionException</code>. It goes 
        without saying that in the latter case, the execute method must declare 
        that it throws this exception. Additionally, Mojos must declare a field 
        for each parameter they specify, and these parameter fields will be 
        populated before execute() is called (Maven does support other 
        mechanisms for parameter injection, but they are not considered part of 
        the preferred practice, and are therefore a topic for an advanced Mojo 
        developer's guide). Finally, all Mojos must be accompanied by metadata 
        describing parameters, lifecycle bindings, etc. This descriptor will be 
        covered in more detail below.</p>
      <p>While this will satisfy the requirements for execution as a Mojo 
        inside Maven, it is recommended that Mojos implement 
         --> Basically, these Mojo requirements are embodied by the 
        <code>org.apache.maven.plugin.Mojo</code> interface, which the Mojo 
        must implement (or else extend its abstract base class counterpart 
        <code>org.apache.maven.plugin.AbstractMojo</code>). This interface 
        guarantees the correct execution contract for the mojo: no parameters, 
        void return type, and a throws clause that allows only 
        <code>org.apache.maven.plugin.MojoExecutionException</code> and its 
        derivatives. It also guarantees that the Mojo will have access to the 
        standard Maven user-feedback mechanism, 
        <code>org.apache.maven.monitor.logging.Log</code>, so the Mojo can 
        communicate important events to the console or other log sink.<!-- Using the 
        Plugin/Mojo API will give that Mojo access to the Maven-integrated Log, 
        along with tighter integration into the Maven build. --></p>
      <p>As mentioned before, each Plugin - or packaged set of Mojos - must 
        provide a descriptor called <code>plugin.xml</code> under the path 
        <code>META-INF/maven</code> inside the Plugin jar file. Fortunately, 
        Maven also provides a set of javadoc annotations and tools to generate 
        this descriptor, so developers don't have to worry about directly 
        authoring or maintaining a separate XML metadata file.</p>
      <p>To serve as a quick reference for the developer, the rest of this page 
        will document these features (the API, along with the annotations) 
        which are considered the best practice for developing Mojos.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="API Documentation">
      <subsection name="org.apache.maven.plugin.Mojo">
        <p>This interface forms the contract required for Mojos to interact 
          with the Maven infrastructure. It features an <code>execute()</code> 
          method, which trigger's the Mojo's build-process behavior, and can 
          throw a <code>MojoExecutionException</code> if an error condition 
          occurs. See below for a discussion on proper use of this 
          <code>Exception</code> class. Also included is the 
          <code>setLog(..)</code> method, which simply allows Maven to inject a 
          logging mechanism which will allow the Mojo to communicate to the 
          outside world through standard Maven channels.</p>
        <p>
          <ul>
            <lt>
              <b>Method Summary:</b>
            </lt>
            <li>
              <code> 
                void setLog( org.apache.maven.monitor.logging.Log ) 
                </code>
              <p>Inject a standard Maven logging mechanism to allow this Mojo 
                to communicate events and feedback to the user.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <code> 
                void execute() throws org.apache.maven.plugin.MojoExecutionException 
                </code>
              <p>Perform whatever build-process behavior this Mojo implements. 
                This is the main trigger for the Mojo inside the Maven system, 
                and allows the Mojo to communicate fatal errors by throwing an 
                instance of <code>MojoExecutionException</code>.</p>
              <p>The <code>MojoExecutionException</code> (and all error 
                conditions inside the Mojo) should be handled very carefully. 
                The simple wrapping of lower-level exceptions without providing 
                any indication of a user-friendly probable cause is strictly 
                discouraged. In fact, a much better course of action is to 
                provide error handling code (try/catch stanzas) for each 
                coherent step within the Mojo's execution. Developers are then 
                in a much better position to diagnose the cause of any error, 
                and provide user-friendly feedback in the message of the 
                <code>MojoExecutionException</code>.</p>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="org.apache.maven.plugin.AbstractMojo">
        <p>Currently, this abstract base class simply takes care of managing 
          the Maven log for concrete derivations. In keeping with this, it 
          provides a <code>protected</code> method, <code>getLog():Log</code>, 
          to furnish Log access to these concrete implementations.</p>
        <p>
          <ul>
            <lt>
              <b>Method Summary:</b>
            </lt>
            <li>
              <code> 
                public void setLog( org.apache.maven.monitor.logging.Log ) 
                </code>
              <p>
                <b>[IMPLEMENTED]</b>
              </p>
              <p>Inject a standard Maven logging mechanism to allow this Mojo 
                to communicate events and feedback to the user.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <code>protected Log getLog()</code>
              <p>
                <b>[IMPLEMENTED]</b>
              </p>
              <p>Furnish access to the standard Maven logging mechanism which 
                is managed in this base class.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <code> 
                void execute() throws org.apache.maven.plugin.MojoExecutionException 
                </code>
              <p>
                <b>[ABSTRACT]</b>
              </p>
              <p>Perform whatever build-process behavior this Mojo implements. 
                See the documentation for <code>Mojo</code> above for more 
                information.</p>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="org.apache.maven.monitor.logging.Log">
        <p>This interface supplies the API for providing feedback to the user 
          from the Mojo, using standard Maven channels. There should be no big 
          surprises here, although you may notice that the methods accept 
          <code>java.lang.CharSequence</code> rather than 
          <code>java.lang.String</code>. This is provided mainly as a 
          convenience, to enable developers to pass things like 
          <code>StringBuffer</code> directly into the logger, rather than 
          formatting first by calling <code>toString()</code>.</p>
        <p>
          <ul>
            <lt>
              <b>Method Summary:</b>
            </lt>
            <li>
              <code> void debug( java.lang.CharSequence ) </code>
              <p>Send a message to the user in the <b>debug</b> error level.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <code> 
                void debug( java.lang.CharSequence, java.lang.Throwable ) 
                </code>
              <p>Send a message (and accompanying exception) to the user in the 
                <b>debug</b> error level. The error's stacktrace will be output 
                when this error level is enabled.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <code> void debug( java.lang.Throwable ) </code>
              <p>Send an exception to the user in the <b>debug</b> error level. 
                The stack trace for this exception will be output when this 
                error level is enabled.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <code> void info( java.lang.CharSequence ) </code>
              <p>Send a message to the user in the <b>info</b> error level.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <code> 
                void info( java.lang.CharSequence, java.lang.Throwable ) 
                </code>
              <p>Send a message (and accompanying exception) to the user in the 
                <b>info</b> error level. The error's stacktrace will be output 
                when this error level is enabled.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <code> void info( java.lang.CharSequence ) </code>
              <p>Send an exception to the user in the <b>info</b> error level. 
                The stack trace for this exception will be output when this 
                error level is enabled.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <code> void warn( java.lang.CharSequence ) </code>
              <p>Send a message to the user in the <b>warn</b> error level.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <code> 
                void warn( java.lang.CharSequence, java.lang.Throwable ) 
                </code>
              <p>Send a message (and accompanying exception) to the user in the 
                <b>warn</b> error level. The error's stacktrace will be output 
                when this error level is enabled.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <code> void warn( java.lang.CharSequence ) </code>
              <p>Send an exception to the user in the <b>warn</b> error level. 
                The stack trace for this exception will be output when this 
                error level is enabled.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <code> void error( java.lang.CharSequence ) </code>
              <p>Send a message to the user in the <b>error</b> error level.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <code> 
                void error( java.lang.CharSequence, java.lang.Throwable ) 
                </code>
              <p>Send a message (and accompanying exception) to the user in the 
                <b>error</b> error level. The error's stacktrace will be output 
                when this error level is enabled.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <code> void error( java.lang.CharSequence ) </code>
              <p>Send an exception to the user in the <b>error</b> error level. 
                The stack trace for this exception will be output when this 
                error level is enabled.</p>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    <section name="The Descriptor and Annotations">
      <p>In addition to the normal Java requirements in terms of interfaces 
        and/or abstract base classes which need to be implemented, a plugin 
        descriptor must accompany these classes inside the plugin jar. This 
        descriptor file is used to provide metadata about the parameters and 
        other component requirements for a set of Mojos so that Maven can 
        initialize the Mojo and validate it's configuration before executing 
        it. As such, the plugin descriptor has a certain set of information 
        that is required for each Mojo specification to be valid, as well as 
        requirements for the overall plugin descriptor itself.</p>
      <p>NOTE: In the following discussion, bolded items are the descriptor's 
        element name along with a javadoc annotation (if applicable) supporting 
        that piece of the plugin descriptor. A couple of examples are: 
        <b>someElement 
        (@annotation parameterName="parameterValue")</b> or 
        <b>someOtherElement (@annotation &lt;rawAnnotationValue&gt;)</b>.</p>
      <p>The plugin descriptor must be provided in a jar resource with the 
        path: <code>META-INF/maven/plugin.xml</code>, and it must contain the 
        following:</p>
      <p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Descriptor Element</th>
            <th>Required?</th>
            <th>Notes</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>mojos</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td>Descriptors for each Mojo provided by the plugin, each inside a 
              <b>mojo</b> sub-element. Mojo descriptors are covered in detail 
              below. Obviously, a plugin without any declared mojos doesn't 
              make sense, so the <b>mojos</b> element is required, along with 
              at least one <b>mojo</b> sub-element.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>dependencies</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td>A set of dependencies which the plugin requires in order to 
              function. Each dependency is provided inside a <b>dependency</b> 
              sub-element. Dependency specifications are covered below. Since 
              all plugins must have a dependency on 
              <code>maven-plugin-api</code>, this element is effectively 
              required. <i>Using the plugin toolset, these dependencies can be 
              extracted from the POM's dependencies.</i></td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </p>
      <p>Each Mojo specified inside a plugin descriptor must provide the 
        following (annotations specified here are at the class level):</p>
      <p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Descriptor Element</th>
            <th>Annotation</th>
            <th>Required?</th>
            <th>Notes</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>goal</td>
            <td>@goal &lt;goalName&gt;</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td>The name for the Mojo that users will reference from the 
              command line to execute the Mojo directly, or inside a POM in 
              order to provide Mojo-specific configuration.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>implementation</td>
            <td>none (detected)</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td>The Mojo's fully-qualified class name (or script path in 
              the case of non-java mojos).</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>language</td>
            <td>none (detected)</td>
            <td>No. Default: <code>java</code></td>
            <td>The implementation language for this Mojo (marmalade, java, 
              beanshell, etc.).</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>configurator</td>
            <td>none (detected)</td>
            <td>No</td>
            <td>The configurator type to use when injecting parameter values 
              into this Mojo. <i>NOTE: This will only be used in very special 
              cases, using a highly controlled vocabulary of possible values. 
              (Elements like this are why it's a good idea to use the 
              descriptor tools.)</i></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>phase</td>
            <td>@phase &lt;phaseName&gt;</td>
            <td>No</td>
            <td>Binds this Mojo to a particular phase of the standard build 
              lifecycle, if specified. <i>NOTE: This is only required if this 
              Mojo is to participate in the standard build process.</i></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>executePhase</td>
            <td>@executePhase &lt;phaseName&gt;</td>
            <td>No</td>
            <td>When this Mojo's goal is invoked directly from the command 
              line, <b>executePhase</b> specifies the last phase in the 
              standard build lifecycle to execute before this Mojo 
              executes.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>requiresDependencyResolution</td>
            <td>@requiresDependencyResolution &lt;requiredScope&gt;</td>
            <td>No</td>
            <td>Flags this Mojo as requiring the dependencies in the specified 
              scope (or an implied scope) to be resolved before it can execute. 
              <i>NOTE: Currently supports <b>compile</b>, 
              <b>runtime</b>, and <b>test</b> scopes.</i></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>description</td>
            <td>none (detected)</td>
            <td>No</td>
            <td>The description of this Mojo's functionality. <i>Using the 
              toolset, this will be the class-level javadoc description 
              provided. NOTE: While this is not a required part of the mojo 
              specification, it SHOULD be provided to enable future 
              tool support for browsing, etc. and for clarity.</i></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>parameters</td>
            <td>N/A</td>
            <td>No</td>
            <td>Specifications for the parameters which this Mojo uses will be 
              provided in <b>parameter</b> sub-elements in this section. 
              <i>NOTE: Parameters are discussed in more detail below.</i></td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </p>
      <p>Each Mojo specifies the parameters that it expects to be able to work 
        with. These parameters are the Mojo's link to the outside world, and 
        will be satisfied through a combination of POM/project values, plugin 
        configurations (from the POM and configuration defaults), and System 
        properties.</p>
      <p>NOTE[1]: For this discussion on Mojo parameters, a single 
        annotation may span multiple elements in the descriptor's specification 
        for that parameter. Duplicate annotation declarations in this section 
        will be used to detail each parameter of an annotation separately.</p>
      <p>NOTE[2]: In many cases, simply annotating a Mojo field with 
        <b>@parameter</b> will be enough to allow injection of a value for that 
        parameter using POM configuration elements. The discussion below 
        shows advanced usage for this annotation, along with others.</p>
      <p>Each parameter for a Mojo must be specified in the 
        plugin descriptor as follows:</p>
      <p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Descriptor Element</th>
            <th>Annotation</th>
            <th>Required?</th>
            <th>Notes</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>name</td>
            <td>none (detected)</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td>The name of the parameter, to be used in configuring this 
              parameter from the Mojo's declared defaults (discussed below) or 
              from the POM. <i>Using the toolset, this is detected as the 
              java field name.</i></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>alias</td>
            <td>@parameter alias="myAlias"</td>
            <td>No</td>
            <td>Specifies an alias which can be used to configure this 
              parameter from the POM. This is primarily useful to improve 
              user-friendliness, where Mojo field names are not intuitive to 
              the user or are otherwise not conducive to configuration via 
              the POM.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>type</td>
            <td>none (detected)</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td>The java type for this parameter. This is used to validate the 
              result of any expressions used to calculate the value which 
              should be injected into the Mojo for this parameter. <i>Using the 
              toolset, this is detected as the class of the java field 
              corresponding to this parameter.</i></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>required</td>
            <td>@required</td>
            <td>No</td>
            <td>Whether this parameter is required for the Mojo to function. 
              This is used to validate the configuration for a Mojo before it 
              is injected, and before the Mojo is executed from some 
              half-state. <i>NOTE: Specification of this annotation flags 
              the parameter as required; there is no true/false value.</i></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>editable</td>
            <td>@readonly</td>
            <td>No</td>
            <td>Specifies that this parameter cannot be configured directly by 
              the user (as in the case of POM-specified configuration). This is 
              useful when you want to force the user to use common POM elements 
              rather than plugin configurations, as in the case where you want 
              to use the artifact's final name as a parameter. In this case, 
              you want the user to modify 
              &lt;build&gt;&lt;finalName/&gt;&lt/build&gt; rather than 
              specifying a value for finalName directly in the plugin 
              configuration section. It is also useful to ensure that - for 
              example - a List-typed parameter which expects items of type 
              Artifact doesn't get a List full of Strings. <i>NOTE: 
              Specification of this annotation flags the parameter as 
              non-editable; there is no true/false value.</i></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>description</td>
            <td>none (detected)</td>
            <td>No</td>
            <td>The description of this parameter's use inside the Mojo. 
              <i>Using the toolset, this is detected as the javadoc description 
              for the field. NOTE: While this is not a required part of the 
              parameter specification, it SHOULD be provided to enable future 
              tool support for browsing, etc. and for clarity.</i></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>expression</td>
            <td>@parameter expression="${someExpression}"</td>
            <td>No</td>
            <td>Specifies the expression used to calculate the value to be 
              injected into this parameter of the Mojo at buildtime. This is 
              commonly used to refer to specific elements in the POM, such as 
              ${project.build.resources}, which refers to the List of resources 
              meant to accompany the classes in the resulting jar file. 
              <i>NOTE: If not specified, an expression of ${&lt;name&gt;} is 
              assumed, which can only be satisfied from POM configuration or 
              System properties. The use of '${' and '}' is required to delimit 
              actual expressions which may be evaluated.</i></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>deprecated</td>
            <td>@deprecated</td>
            <td>No</td>
            <td>Marks a parameter as deprecated. The rules on deprecation are 
              the same as normal java with language elements. This will trigger 
              a warning when a user tries to configure a parameter marked as 
              deprecated. </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </p>
      <p>The final component of a plugin descriptor is the dependencies. This 
        enables the plugin to function independently of it's POM (or at least 
        to declare the libraries it needs to run). Dependencies are taken from 
        the <b>runtime</b> scope of the plugin's calculated dependencies (from 
        the POM). Dependencies are specified in exactly the same manner as in 
        the POM, except for the &lt;scope&gt; element (all dependencies in the 
        plugin descriptor are assumed to be runtime, because this is a 
        runtime profile for the plugin).</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Plugin Tools">
      <p>By now, we've mentioned the plugin tools several times without telling 
        you what they are or how to use them. Instead of manually writing (and 
        maintaining) the metadata detailed above, Maven 2.0 ships with some 
        tools to aid in this task. In fact, the only thing a plugin developer 
        needs to do is declare his project to be a plugin from within the POM. 
        Once this is done, Maven will call the appropriate descriptor 
        generators, etc. to produce an artifact that is ready for use within 
        Maven builds. Optional metadata can be injected via javadoc annotation 
        (and possibly jdk5 annotations in the future) as described above, 
        enabling richer interactions between the Mojo and the user. The 
        section below describes the changes to the POM which are necessary to 
        create plugin artifacts.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Project Descriptor (POM) Requirements">
      <p>From the POM, Maven plugin projects look quite similar to any other 
        project. For pure java plugins, the differences are even smaller than 
        for script-based plugins. The following details the POM elements 
        which are necessary to build a Maven plugin artifact.</p>
      <p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>POM Element</th>
            <th>Required for Java Mojos?</th>
            <th>Sample Declaration</th>
            <th>Notes</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>packaging</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td><code>&lt;packaging&gt;maven-plugin&lt;/packaging&gt;</code></td>
            <td>The POM must declare a packaging element which describes this 
              project as a Maven plugin project.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>scriptSourceDirectory</td>
            <td>No</td>
            <td><code>&lt;scriptSourceDirectory&gt;src/main/scripts&lt;/scriptSourceDirectory&gt;</code></td>
            <td>In the case of script-based Mojos (which are not covered in 
              detail within this document), the POM must include an additional 
              element to distinguish script sources from (optional) java 
              supporting classes. This element is the scriptSourceDirectory, 
              inside the build section. This directory is included in the list 
              of resources which accompany any compiled code in the resulting 
              artifact. It is specified separately from the resources in the 
              build section to denote its special status as an alternate source 
              directory for scripts.</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </p>
      <p>After making the changes above, the developer can simply call 
        <br/><br/><code>m2 install</code><br/><br/> to install the plugin to 
        the local repository. (Any of the other standard lifecycle targets like 
        package, deploy, etc. are also available in like fashion.)</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Resources">
      <p>This section simply gives a listing of pointers for more 
        information.</p>
      <p>
        <ul>
          <li>M2 Plugin Overview [<a 
            href="plugin-overview.html">link</a>]</li>
          <li>QDox Project (javadoc annotations) [<a 
            href="http://qdox.codehaus.org">link</a>]</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>