<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Available Plugins</title>
    <author email="brett@apache.org">Brett Porter</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Available Plugins">
      <p>
        This page lists some of the available plugins for Maven 2.0. Please bear in mind that this is not a definitive
        list, and that others can be made available immediately via the Maven repository. 
      </p>
      <p>
        To see the most up-to-date list of available plugins, browse the Maven 2 plugin repository
        at <a href="http://www.ibiblio.org/maven2/plugins/">http://www.ibiblio.org/maven2/plugins/</a>.  
        Plugins are organized according to a directory structure that resembles
        the standard Java package naming convention.  To see a list of available
        plugins from the Maven project, look in the <a href="http://www.ibiblio.org/maven2/plugins/org/apache/maven/plugins/">org/apache/maven subfolder</a>
        of this directory.
      </p>
      <p>
        Full documentation on each of these plugins is still in the works - contributions are welcome!
      </p>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>Plugin</th>
          <th>Description</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-ant-plugin"><code>ant</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Generate an Ant build file for the project
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-archetype-plugin"><code>archetype</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Generate a skeleton project structure from an archetype.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-assembly-plugin"><code>assembly</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Build an assembly (distribution) of sources and binaries.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-clean-plugin"><code>clean</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Clean up after the build.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-compiler-plugin"><code>compiler</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Compiles Java sources.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-deploy-plugin"><code>deploy</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Deploy the built artifact to the remote repository.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-eclipse-plugin"><code>eclipse</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Generate an Eclipse project file for the current project.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-ejb-plugin"><code>ejb</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Build an EJB (and optional client) from the current project.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-idea-plugin"><code>idea</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Create/update an IDEA workspace for the current project (individual modules are created as IDEA modules)
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-install-plugin"><code>install</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Install the built artifact into the local repository.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-jar-plugin"><code>jar</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Build a JAR from the current project.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-plugin-plugin"><code>plugin</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Create a Maven plugin descriptor for any Mojo's found in the source tree, to include in the JAR.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-resources-plugin"><code>resources</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Copy the resources to the output directory for including in the JAR.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-site-plugin"><code>site</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Generate a site for the current project.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-source-plugin"><code>source</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Build a JAR of sources for use in IDEs and distribution to the repository.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-surefire-plugin"><code>surefire</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Run the Junit tests in an isolated classloader.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-verifier-plugin"><code>verifier</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Useful for integration tests - verifies the existence of certain conditions.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="maven-war-plugin"><code>war</code></a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Build a WAR from the current project.
          </td>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

